Guide to the Burt D. Wells Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Burt D. Wells papers
1950-1971
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6176
6176-001
Wells, Burt D.
3.6 cubic feet 4 boxes
Papers of paper worker union organizer and officer Burt D. Wells related to his involvement with the International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers, Local 242 of Portland, Oregon; the revolt of the Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action; and the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers.
Burt D. Wells was President of the International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers (IBPS&PMW) Local 242 in Portland, Oregon. Wells also served as Secretary-Treasurer of the Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action in the late 1950s-early 1960s, a committee formed by members of IBPS&PMW locals in protest of decisions made by the International leadership, including the dismissal of Research and Education Director, George Brooks in 1961. These and similar efforts within paper worker unions across the U.S. and Canada resulted in the establishment of rebel union, the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers in 1964 where many dissatisfied members of the IBPS&PMW and United Papermakers and Paperworkers relocated themselves.
The collection is arranged into the following series and subseries:
SERIES 1: RANK AND FILE MOVEMENT FOR DEMOCRATIC ACTION
Subseries A: Correspondence
Subseries B: Individual Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Member Correspondence
Subseries C: Meetings and Conventions
Subseries D: Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Financial and Administrative Records
SERIES 2: INTERNATIONAL BROTHERHOOD OF PULP, SULPHITE AND PAPER MILL WORKERS
Subseries A: International
Subseries B: Rose City Local 242, Portland, Oregon
SERIES 3: ASSOCIATION OF WESTERN PULP AND PAPER WORKERS
SERIES 4: PUBLISHED MATERIAL
Papers of paper worker union organizer and officer, Burt D. Wells, consisting primarily of records related to his involvement with the Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action and the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers, including correspondence, newsletters, legal files, reports, press, and flyers as well as general correspondence and other records related to the International Brotherhood of Pulp Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers and Local 242 in Portland, Oregon. There is considerable overlap of related materials across series and subseries but maintained to respect the arrangement of the materials prior to processing.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
Collection is open for research use but records are stored offsite; advance notice is required for use.
Donated by Rosa Millo Eyer, originally a part of the John H. Eyer papers (3932-001), 1987-09-14
Due to the collection's distinctiveness as a body of records belonging to Burt D. Wells and the material's historical significance, this collection was separated from the first accession of the
John H. Eyer Papers (Manuscript Accession 3932-001)
during processing in December 2017.
Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers records (manuscript collection 2052)
Wells, Burt D.$vArchives; International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite, and Paper Mill Workers; Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action; Labor unions$zOregon; Labor union members$zOregon; Labor unions$zOregon$xOfficials and employees; Labor$zOregon; Labor movement$zOregon; Records (Documents); Personal correspondence; Newsletters; Ephemera; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Portland
- RANK AND FILE MOVEMENT FOR DEMOCRATIC ACTION, 1953-1965; SERIES 1 (Box-folder 1/1-3/2)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1965; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/1-26)
    - Correspondence: Dismissal of George Brooks, Appointment of Jerald Hatt Controversy, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Regional Correspondence: Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Correspondence with Locals: Protest Letters Regarding Firing of George Brooks, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Correspondence: Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Correspondence with Locals Around United States: Detroit Convention, 1962 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Correspondence: Brooks Dismissal, United Papermakers and Paperworkers and Frank Grasso, Detroit Convention, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Convention, Detroit, Michigan: Burt Wells' Convention Materials [1 of 2], 1962 (Box-folder 1/7)
      Contains full issues of the following print publications: Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers' Journal, Vol. XLVI, No. 1, Jan-Feb 1962; Clean-UPP, Vol. 2 No. 2, May-June 1963; Pulp & Paper Worker, Vol. 17, No. 2, 1962 August; Oregon Labor Press, Vol. 63, No. 38, Portland, September 21, 1962
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Convention, Detroit, Michigan: Burt Wells' Convention Materials [2 of 2], 1962 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers 26th Annual Convention, Detroit, Michigan: Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Local Delegates and Proposed Resolutions, 1962 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Correspondence: George Brooks' Dismissal [1 of 2], 1961 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Correspondence: George Brooks' Dismissal [2 of 2], 1961 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Gerard Schmidt Firing Case at International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Local 318, Glen Cove, New York, 1962 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Proposal for Constitutional Reform for Elections, 1962 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers General Correspondence, 1961 May-December (Box-folder 1/14)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers General Correspondence, 1962 January-May (Box-folder 1/15)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers General Correspondence, 1962 June-December (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Union Locals Correspondence: George Brooks Resignation, 1961 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Quarterly Audit Report Inquiry by Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action, circa 1960-1962 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - United Papermakers and Paperworkers, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - F.J. Tierney's Resignation Letter to President Burke, 1962 May 9 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Opposition [1 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Opposition [2 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Opposition to Appointment of Jerald Hatt as International Representative, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Support for Reinstatement of George Brooks, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - International Officer Correspondence: George Brooks' Resignation and Southwest Area Staff, 1961 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Burt Wells' Correspondence with University of Wisconsin and Wisconsin State Historical Society: Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Records, 1964-1965; This file contains correspondence related to the loan of RFMDA records to archives for microfilming (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Individual Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Member Correspondence, 1960-1964; Subseries B (Box-folder 1/27-2/22)
    - Amden, Richard, Local 183, Everett, Washington, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Ballantyne, James, President, Local 89, Kapuskasing, Ontario, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Bartlett, Harold M., Local 22, Fort Orange, New York, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Benson, Herman W., Editor of Union Democracy in Action newsletter, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Bevan, Edwin C., Treasurer of Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action, 1962 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - Braaten, Orville, Business Agent, Local 433, Vancouver, British Columbia, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Chatham, R. H., West Monroe Local 512, Louisiana, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Dukes, Clarence W., San Joaquin Local 713, Antioch, California, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Cowman, William H., President of Local 400, Brunswick, Georgia, 1962 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Farrace, Arthur, Antioch, California, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - McCormick, Bob, Western Canada Council, Ocean Falls, British Columbia, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - MacPhee, Angus, Watson Island Local 708, Prince Rupert, British Columbia: Committee of Inquiry, Cuba Trip and Communist Allegations, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Marshall, Peter, Secretary-Treasurer of Western Canada Area Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action, Local 312, Ocean Falls, British Columbia, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Melton, Melvin, Secretary of Local 194, Bellingham, Washington, 1960-1964; Includes essays submitted by union members to story contest about corruption in the International. (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Mercer, Graham, Local 169, Hoquiam, Washington, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Perrin, William, Local 68, West Linn, Oregon, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Rodgers, Henry, Local 375, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania [1 of 2], 1961-1963 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Rodgers, Henry, Local 375, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania [2 of 2], 1961-1963; Contains issue of Local 375 East Coast Newsletter (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Rosebush, George, Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Area Chairman for Ontario and Manitoba, Local 89, Kapuskasing, Ontario, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Ruddick, Godfrey J., International Vice-President, Little Rock, Arkansas, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Savage, Leo R., President of United Gilman Local 41, Gilman, Vermont, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Scarselletta, Mario, President of Hudson River Local 20, Glens Falls, New York, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Schmidt, Herbert, Secretary of South Gate Local 253 Correspondence: 1962 Election Dispute and Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Stanley, L. R., Secretary, Local 171, Vancouver, Washington: Anti-Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Sterman, Albert, Local 375, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Correspondence with International about John McNiff and Education Spending, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Stewart, L. E., President, Local 253, South Gate, California Correspondence: Election Dispute, 1962 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - Wilner, Don S., Correspondence with Burt Wells and William Perrin, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Meetings and Conventions, 1959-1963; Subseries C (Box-folder 2/23-32)
    - Northwest Committee for Union Justice: Correspondence and Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/23)
    - British Columbia Committee of Inquiry Minutes: George Brooks Resignation, 1961 (Box-folder 2/24)
    - Western Canada Area of the Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action: Meeting Minutes, 1961 (Box-folder 2/25)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action: Mid-Atlantic States Conference Meeting Minutes, 1961 June 3 (Box-folder 2/26)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action: Southeast Area Conference Meeting Minutes, 1962 March 3 (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Area Executive Conference, Denver, Colorado: Meeting Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/28)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Local 89, Kapuskasing, Ontario: Special Meeting on Connolly and Hayes Dismissal, 1960 August 28 (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Meeting Minutes of Joseph Tonelli's Staff at Prince George Hotel, 1961 March (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Western Canada Council of Pulp and Paper Mill Unions Spring Conference in Vancouver, British Columbia: Meeting Minutes, 1962 May 14 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - United Papermakers and Paperworkers: Correspondence, Reports, Court Records, Newsletters, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Financial and Administrative Records, 1953-1964; Subseries D (Box-folder 2/33-3/2)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Per Capita Dues Payments [1 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/33)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Per Capita Dues Payments [2 of 2], 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - Amplifier Subscribers, Paper Worker Members, and Executive Officers Mailing Lists, circa 1953-1964 (Box-folder 2/35)
    - Reform Movement Background: Assorted Writings by Burt Wells and Others, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 2/36)
    - Reform Movement: Burt Wells' Affidavit and Court Exhibit Files, circa 1957-1964 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Handbook for Constitutional Reform, circa 1962 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Rank and File Movement for Democratic Action Financial Statements and Receipt Logs, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 3/2)
- INTERNATIONAL BROTHERHOOD OF PULP, SULPHITE AND PAPER MILL WORKERS, 1950-1964; SERIES 2 (Box-folder 3/3-23)
  - International, 1958-1964; Subseries A (Box-folder 3/3-11)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers General Correspondence [1 of 2], 1959-1960 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers General Correspondence [2 of 2], 1959-1960 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Financial Quarterly Reports, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Reports of the Auditor, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Complete Report of the Special Investigating Committee [on Vice President Joseph Tonelli], 1960 September 20 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Report of Union Job Evaluation Committee, 1963 January 14 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers and United Papermakers and Paperworkers Pre-Wage Conference Minutes, 1959 May 11 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - International Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Paper Worker Union Local Rosters and Officers Lists, circa 1960-1964 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Rose City Local 242, Portland, Oregon, 1950-1963; Subseries B (Box-folder 3/12-23)
    - Local 242 Resolution Proposals to International President-Secretary, 1962 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - External Correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Wage Stabilization Board Correspondence, 1951-1963 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Local and International Resolutions, circa 1957-1963 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Rose City Local 242 Information for New Members, circa 1950-1957 (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Portland and Salem, Oregon Labor Councils: Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Local 242 Internal Correspondence [1 of 2], 1955-1963 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Local 242 Internal Correspondence [2 of 2], 1955-1963 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Unemployment Benefits Information, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Correspondence to and from International and Local 242 Quarterly Reports, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Local 242 Financial Report, 1957 (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Artifact: Burt D. Wells' Detroit Convention Ribbon and Medal Pin, 1962 (Box-folder 3/23)
- ASSOCIATION OF WESTERN PULP AND PAPER WORKERS, 1952-1971; SERIES 3 (Box-folder 3/24-46)
  - Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers: Correspondence, Minutes, Reports, Published Material, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Election Campaign: Flyers and Press, circa 1967 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Attorney Retainer Fee Policy, 1966 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Burt Wells' Letter of Credentials as Representative of the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers, 1964 October 8 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Uniform Labor Agreement Committee Draft Bylaws, circa 1964 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Burt Wells' Personal Correspondence, 1952-1965 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Presidents William Perrin and Hugh Bannister: Correspondence, Ephemera, Press, 1962-1970 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Burt Wells' Secretary-Treasurer Reports to the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers, circa 1964-1967 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - Transcript of Wayne Morse's Keynote Speech at the 4th Annual Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers Convention, 1969 September 15 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Draft of The Paper Rebellion: The Story of the Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers by Paul L. Kleinsorge and William C. Kerby, 1966 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - H.W. Benson's Article on Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers in Union Democracy in Action, 1967 (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Elections: Flyers, Press, and Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - Referendum Election, 1967 (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Local 7 Pipefitters Union Picket at Boise-Cascade Plant in Salem, Oregon, 1967 (Box-folder 3/37)
  - Local 153, Longview, Washington: Picket Line Crossing, 1964 December (Box-folder 3/38)
  - Local 672 Newsletter The Little Rebel, 1967 January (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Office Policies and Personal Issues, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Southern Washington Area Council Meeting Minutes, 1968 April (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Burt Wells' Secretary-Treasurer Quarterly Report, 1970 March 31 (Box-folder 3/42)
  - Local 64, Portland, Oregon: Executive Board Newsletter, 1970 December 14 (Box-folder 3/43)
  - Local 6 and 68 Election Rules Violations, 1970 (Box-folder 3/44)
  - The Necessity of Reform in the Pulp and Paper Union Movement Report, circa 1964 (Box-folder 3/45)
  - Assorted Correspondence and Reports, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 3/46)
- PUBLISHED MATERIAL, 1953-1965; SERIES 4 (Box-folder 3/47-4/8)
  - Assorted News Clippings on Paper Worker Unions in the Pacific Northwest [1 of 2], 1964-1965 (Box-folder 3/47)
  - Assorted News Clippings on Paper Worker Unions in the Pacific Northwest [2 of 2], 1964-1965 (Box-folder 3/48)
  - Portland Reporter News Clippings on Paper Workers, 1964 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Post Record Newspaper of Camas and Washougal, Washington: Clippings on Paper Workers Union, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - The Broke Beater Newsletter of International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Local 153, Longview, Washington, 1964 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Clean UPP Newsletter of the United Papermakers and Paperworkers, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Employee Welfare Trust Funds, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Assorted Articles, Pamphlets, and Handouts, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Political Memo Newsletter of the AFL-CIO, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Union Democracy in Action Issues and Publicity, circa 1959-1962 (Box-folder 4/8)